A Guide to the Kate Carper Papers, 1861-1976
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Kate Carper Papers, 1861-1976
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-30
.25 linear feet
The Kate Carper Papers collection consists of 0.25 linear feet and spans the years 1861-1976 and contains typescript copies of her diary entries from the Civil War years of 1861-1863, transcripts and photocopies of some correspondence, and a list of events from the later years of 1899-1924.
Carper, Catherine Louise (Kate) (1834-1924)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Received as gift from Cordelia G. Sansone, 1976.
Historical and Biographical Information
The Civil War diaries of Miss Kate Carper are reproduced from a book belonging to her sister which was in the Civil War collection of Mr. Richard Hammond in 1976. Kate Carper lived at Bloomfield in Dranesville, VA. Bloomfield was named by Frederick Carper in 1824 and was the home of that branch of the Carper family (a branch of the family that built Colvin Run Mill) until 1924. Ms. Carper, the daughter of Frederick and Martha Mead Carper was educated first at Mrs. Edwards School for Girls, and subsequently at Coombe Cottage in Fairfax. Ms. Carper remained unmarried and was involved in running the household in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries until her death in 1924.
Scope and Content
The Kate Carper Papers collection consists of 0.25 linear feet and spans the years 1861-1976 and contains typescript copies of her diary entries from the Civil War years of 1861-1863, transcripts and photocopies of some correspondence, and a list of events from the later years of 1899-1924. It also contains typescript copies of expense records from her home "Bloomfield" for the years 1863-1881 and 1910-1924.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
Index Terms
Archer, Capt. John, 1838-1899; Austin, Georgia, 1842-1869; Bellows, Arnold H., 1884-1957; Carper, Catherine Louise (Kate), 1834-1924; Carper, Thomas, 1831-1891; Doubleday, Abner, 1819-1893.; Dranesville (Va.) -- History.; Fairfax County (Va.) -- History.; Fairfax County (Va.) -- History -- 1861-1865, Civil War.; Historic buildings -- Virginia -- Fairfax County.; Hutchinson, Joshua, 1842-1931
Container List
- Unnumbered page describing diary and transcriptions of notes from the volume containing the diary, 20 August 1976
- Diary. (p. 1-9) (Typescript), 1861-1863
- Photocopy of 1863 poem (p. 10), 1863
- Index of other items (on pages numbered 10-20) included with diary (p. 11), Undated
- Letter, Georgia Auston to Kate Carper (p. 12) (Transcript), 1863(?)
- Letter, Abner Doubleday to Mr. Thomas Carper. (p. 13), 7 September 1863
- Letter, Capt. John Archer to __ Carper, (p. 14), 10 September 1865
- Letter, Arnold H. Bellows to Joshua Hutchinson (p. 15-18), 30 September 1930
- Letter, Arnold H. Bellows (p. 19, this letter contained the poem on p. 10 above), 25 October 1930
- Letter, Arnold H. Bellows to widow of Joshua Hutchinson, 2 February 1931
- Record of Expenses at Bloomfield (17 pp.) (Typescript), 1863-1881
- Record of Expenses at Bloomfield (41 pp.) (Typescript), 1910-1924
- Record of Events at Bloomfield (5 pp.) (Typescript), 1899-1924